<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Motives to Godly mourning and rejoycing; or, Christ Jesus his kind invitation to sinners to repent</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2942A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833167</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37642</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51494)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37642)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2192:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Motives to Godly mourning and rejoycing; or, Christ Jesus his kind invitation to sinners to repent</title>
                  <author>W. H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: W.H.</note>
                  <note>A translation of a Latin work; latin original not found.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Dr. Williams' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Attributes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37642:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOTIVES TO Godly Mourning and Rejoycing; OR, Chriſt Jeſus HIS KIND INVITATION TO Sinners to Repent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM CVI. 4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember me, O Lord, according to the favour that thou beareſt unto thy People: O viſit me with thy Salvation!</p>
               <p>That I may ſee the Good of thy Choſen, that I may rejoyce in the Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Nation, that I may glory with thine Inheritance.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. LI. 10, 11, 12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Create in me a clean Heart, O Lord, and renew a right Spirit within me.</p>
               <p>Caſt me not away from thy preſence, and take not thy holy Spirit from me.</p>
               <p>Reſtore unto me the Joy of thy Salvation, and uphold me by thy free Spirit:</p>
               <p>Then will I teach Tranſgreſſours thy ways, and Sinners ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto thee.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37642:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37642:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Reverend, Pious, and Faithful Miniſter of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>John Shower.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Beg your Patronage to this new Brood, which I found in <hi>England,</hi> though (as I ſuppoſe) its origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Father brought it to light in another Land: I found it cloathed in Latin Apparel, and I have put an Engliſh Coat upon it; and I hope that thereby it may be kindly received by many that are in <hi>England,</hi> who have a ſavour of the things of God; as for others, that know not God, I doubt whether they will caſt their Eyes upon it: But if any that are ſuch, take a fancy to look upon it, God grant it may do them good, and that they may be thereby drawn to the Love of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, being allured by his ſweet Entiſements and Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. It was ſweet to me in the Original, and I hope it may be ſo to others in the Tranſlation. I hope you will not be offended that I have made a Dedication of this Book to you without your Conſent; for if I had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted you to give your Conſent to accept of a Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I doubt whether you would have given it; but having dedicated it to you unawares, I hope you cannot be angry for my giving you that, which, before it was given, you had no occaſion to refuſe. What ſucceſs it may have, I am uncertain; but I ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:37642:3"/>it to range and ſeek its fortune in the World, as the Levit of <hi>Bethlem-judah</hi> did, who wandered up and down to ſee if he could find a place, and at length was kindly entertained by <hi>Micah,</hi> and afterwards was made a Father and a Prieſt to a Family and Tribe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But if any deſire to know why I made this Dedication to you; there were many Cauſes why I ſhould do ſo: One of which is, The great Kindneſs that you have ſhewed to my ſelf: <hi>Job</hi> ſaid, the <hi>Bleſſing of him that was almoſt ready to periſh came upon me; and I made the Widow's Heart to ſing.</hi> What Miſery was I in, through Poverty and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, when your Kindneſs, and Charity, and Liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did afford me ſuch ſeaſonable Relief, that it reſembled upon many accounts a Reſurrection from the dead? Therefore I gladly embrace this Opportunity of giving a publick Teſtimony of my Thankfulneſs, that hath a long time lain hid in my Heart, and is now triumphantly glad to ſhew it ſelf in the Light of the Day, and the Sight of the Sun. Moreover, your Name being in the Frontiſpiece of this Book, I hope it may allure many that have ſat under the ſhadow of your Miniſtry, to pay ſome Deference of reſpect to it, and not to grudge the charge of Buying it, nor the labour of Viewing it.</p>
            <p>Sir, your Name is famous in <hi>England;</hi> for in the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of your Miniſtry you have ſurpaſſed many others of your Brethren, that are elder than you. You are like young <hi>Elihu,</hi> that in Wiſdom excelled the Friends of <hi>Job,</hi> that were aged and gray-headed Men, much elder than <hi>Job</hi>'s Father: And in external Honours God hath exalted you above many of your Brethren; ſo that your Name is as young <hi>David</hi>'s was, much ſet by, before he was exalted to the Throne and Dignity of a King.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37642:3"/>
            <p> Sir, what I have ſaid to you, I have not ſaid in Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, but in the Sincerity of my Heart; and therefore I hope theſe external Teſtimonies of the Thankfulneſs that was a long time hid within my Heart, cannot of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Grace of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Your hearty Friend and Servant, and Brother in Chriſt, <hi>W. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:37642:4"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am a Man that hath paſſed through many Calamities in the days of the Years, that I have lived in the World. My Mother brought me forth in <hi>Scotland,</hi> half a Year after <hi>Cromwell</hi> had paſſed through <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> with Fire and Sword; and it is likely my Mother was at that time, by reaſon of thoſe bloody and cruel Wars, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted with many Amazements when I was in her Womb; and, I ſuppoſe, that hath occaſioned, that I have been fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſubject to ſudden Aſtoniſhments and Conſternations, and Panick Fears, from my Childhood. When I was under Sixteen Years I flouriſhed with outward Proſperity, and almoſt conſtantly delighted my ſelf with the abundance of Peace; being beloved and honoured of all that knew me far and near: Which occaſioned me to be puffed up in my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; till Affliction of ſeveral Kinds ſent of God for my Good, had brought down that Vanity of my Mind. When I was fourteen or fifteen Years of age, I frequented a School at <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> where I greatly profited in variety of Learning, and attained to a great inſight of the Poetical Faculty: After I had been at that School, I was a while at <hi>Leyden;</hi> where I ſtudied <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Metaphyſick,</hi> though at that time alſo I laboured diligently in prying into the Myſteries of Poeſie. After I had been a while at <hi>Leyden,</hi> I went into <hi>Scotland;</hi> where I ſtudied <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and received the Degree of Maſter of Arts. And at that time alſo I diligently ſtudied and exerciſed Poeſie, and made a Poem on <hi>Job,</hi> which hath been well approved by many learned Men: I made all that Poem, before I was twenty Years old; for my Spirit was then much ſtrengthned by general reſpect, that was ſhewed to me by many of thoſe with whom I converſed, and by the Kindneſs of my Brother in law, that married one of my
<pb facs="tcp:37642:4"/>Siſters: He was a Man eminent both in Wiſdom and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and maintained me above a Year on his own Caſt; and was then kinder to me, than was my own Father, out of whoſe Bowels I proceeded. After I was eighteen Years of Age I went to my Father's Houſe, who was then, and had been a long time, a Miniſter in <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> and the ſpace of two or three Years I lived on my Father's Charges, and at that time I was greatly afflicted in my Spirit, partly through my Father's Churliſhneſs and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nkindneſs, and partly through inward Griefs and Diſcontents of Mind, that I ſuffered through ſome great and grievous Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that befel me: At that time I was much in Prayer; I was often fervently calling upon my God with Weeping and Supplication; and though then I did not diſcern, that God took any notice of the Prayers I made to him in thoſe great Afflictions, yet ſince that time I have had clear Eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that I did not call upon God in vain. After my Father had, upon his Coſt maintained me two or three Years, I travelled into <hi>England;</hi> where I ſuffered Poverty ſeveral Years, and did often eat Bread of Affliction, and drank Water of Affliction: Yet in that time I had ſome ſweet Intervals of Divine Conſolation, when I had Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities occaſionally to preach in the days of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second: For it was a great Joy to me at that time, that I had Opportunities to ſerve <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> though I ſuffered ſometimes Perſecution. But one of the things that greatly allayed my Sorrows and Diſcontents, was the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Divine Conſolation, I received by having heard ſometimes occaſionally that great Miniſter of Chriſt, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Cole,</hi> who died a while ſince: For in hearing him preach, at ſometimes ſuch Beams of Divine Light did ſhine forth upon my Soul, ſuch glorious Manifeſtations of the Love of God did over-ſhadow me, that it made many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, that I then and ſince have endured, to become light
<pb facs="tcp:37642:5"/>and eaſie: For in the ſtrength of thoſe Diſcoveries of the Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, I have walked many days in the Light of God's Countenance. But becauſe I have been guilty of ſome Infirmities through violent Temptations, wherewith God hath ſuffered Satan to aſſault me; ſome, if they are not of a charitable Spirit, may think theſe things are Hypocritical Dreams, und Chimerical Imaginations; but I know him, whom I have believed: But theſe things I have publickly declared, that none of thoſe that fear God may be aſhamed for my ſake. If you ask the cauſe why I have given this Book the title of <hi>Motives to Godly Mourning and Rejoycing:</hi> This is one Cauſe thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Godly Sorrow is the Seed of Godly Joy and Rejoycing, as the Saints have often found by their Experience, to whoſe Experience I may appeal. Another Cauſe is this, Becauſe I deſire that wicked Wretches, who have lived without God in the World, be convinced, that if they will heartily apply themſelves to Godlineſs, they will find that Joy and Pleaſure in the Ways of God, not only in the World to come, but alſo in this World, which will greatly ſurpaſs all the Joys and Pleaſures that they have found in the Ways of Sin, and in their Eſtrangement from God. Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I wonder, wretched Sinner, that has lived in Enmity to God, how thou canſt eat or drink, or ſleep in Peace, when the Sword of Vengeance hangs over thy Head, and there is but a ſtep between thee and Hell, and everlaſting fire. But after thou haſt returned to God by repentance, and ſhelter'd thy ſelf by Faith under the Wings of Chriſt Jeſus, then thou mayeſt have juſt cauſe of Rejoycing: I have therefore publiſhed this Book to awaken thee, and ſtir thee up to Repentance, and to fly to Chriſt, the Refuge of Sinners, that thou mayest have much Joy and Peace in believing in this World, and enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to everlaſting Joys and Felicity in the perfect Enjoyment of God and Chriſt in the World to come.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:37642:5"/>
            <head>MOTIVES to Godly Mourning and Rejoycing; or, <hi>CHRIST JESUS</hi> his Kind Invitation to Sinners to Repent.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Concerning the Grief of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>lamenting the Stubbornneſs of a Sinner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I THE Only begotten Son of God, the Power and Wiſdom of God, do cry in the Streets, and lift up my Voice in the midſt of the People; for I have nouriſhed and brought up the Sons of Men, but they have deſpiſed me. O Man! I have written the ſweet Law of my New Teſtament in thy inward parts, and have planted it in the midſt of thy Heart. And yet thou haſt had no deſire to my immaculate Law, which converts the Souls of Sinners; neither haſt thou regarded the ſaithful Teſtimony of my Eternal Love. Thou haſt went far away from me, with the Tranſgreſſour <hi>Adam</hi> thy Father; and thou haſt hid thy ſelf from Me, thy moſt gracious God and Saviour, when I walked in the Garden in the cool of the Day. What meaneth this, thou eſtranged Son? Whither flyeſt thou from the Face of thy moſt merciful God and Redeemer?
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37642:6"/>Am I a cruel Lord, becauſe thou flyeſt ſpeedily away from me, and ſeekeſt to find a better Maſter? Conſider what thou doſt, and how far thou goeſt from thy own Salvation; for without cauſe thou hateſt thy moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Remedy and Liberty. Thy unhappy Soul is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as a Widow; which, if thou wouldeſt cloſe with Divine Grace, might remain faithful to the Covenant of her Eſpouſals, and enjoy the Priviledges of my moſt Sweet Love. And yet ſhe hath abhorred me her moſt faithful Lover, and her Enemies have been enriched with her Spoils. How is the Gold of my ancient Love become dim, the bright-ſhining Colour of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is changed, the Stones of my Temple and Sanctuary are ſcattered upon the top of every Street: Thou didſt not delight in the Habitation of my City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which I have loved, and thou haſt been rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned among the Citizens, which my Soul hates. Wo to the Soul, that departeth from me! for the Terrors of Death will ſet themſelves in aray againſt it, and the Pains of Hell will take hold of it. The Lion's Whelps will rage againſt it, and roar after it, that they may ſnatch it, and take it for Meat thrown to them by God. For ſince thou didſt ſet up the Darkneſs of Sin inſtead of the Light of my Grace, and there came upon thee a moſt diſmal night of my Anger, all the Beaſts of the Inſernal Wood paſs by, and make haſte with open Mouth to devour thy Apoſtate Soul. Therefore, at leaſt from this time, call unto me, and ſay, Thou art my God and my Guide; and now I will no more fly from thee. O moſt gracious God! I have wandered, being a Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gabond, like <hi>Cain,</hi> out of thy ſight; and I have ſerved other Gods, in whom I have no Salvation nor Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Behold, I return unto thee from a grievous Bondage: I ſeek for thy moſt lovely Light from the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:37642:6"/>Darkneſs and Shadow of Death, which hath terrified me. I know of a truth, being convinced by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, that there is no good thing out of thee, the Son of the moſt amiable, and moſt high God, to whom I conſecrate my inward Parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Concerning the Sweetneſs of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>calling a Sinner to Repentance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Wiſh, my Son, that thou wouldeſt prize my Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which is better than Gold, and that thou wouldeſt hearken with the Ears of a contrite and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Heart unto my ſtill Voice, whereunto the Rocks are moved. O <hi>Ephraim!</hi> I as a nurſing Father take care of thee, and my great and moſt faithful Mercy ſtrives with the Hardneſs of thy ſtony Heart. Thou according to thy Hardneſs, and impenitent Heart, reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my Spirit, which is ſweeter than the Honey; and I according to the Riches of infinite Goodneſs, endeavour to mollify thy inward parts with my ſecret and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Inſpirations. Thou flyeſt from me, who am purſuing thee not for Hatred, but for deſign of thy Salvation: And I meet thee flying away as it were by lying in wait, that I may embrace thee with ſtretched forth Arms, and may overcome thy Cruelty with my Infinite Mercy. For which cauſe the Heavens and the Earth wonder at the Clemency and Sweetneſs of their Creator, who watcheth ſo carefully over a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful Sinner, who is not willing to take my ſweet Yoke upon him. How long ſhall thy hard Heart kick a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prick of my moſt ſtrong Love? Wilt thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:37642:7"/>reſiſt the unconceivable Love of thy God? I could have damned thee by my Juſtice, becauſe thou didſt wickedly, and brakeſt my Yoke, and ſaidſt, I will not ſerve: And yet I ſuffered thee in much Patience, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of thy Eternal Life, if perhaps thou wouldeſt turn unto me, and be reconciled to my moſt merciful Father. Why then doſt thou tarry, moſt beloved Son? Why de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layeſt thou from day to day to return unto my moſt ſweet Peace and Love? Suffer me, my Son, ſuffer me to diſſolve thy Ice with the hot burning Fire of my Love, and to renew thy Deformed Soul, according to the Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of the only begotten Son of God. O Off-ſpring of <hi>Adam,</hi> how long ſhall I ſuffer you! O wonderful thing, hidden from the Wiſe and the Prudent of the World, who have ſhut their Ears leaſt they ſhould hear my Heart-warning Speech! I the Son of the moſt High, ſtand at thy door and knock, deſiring to enter in, and fill thy Houſe with unſpeakable good things; and yet it ſeems grievous to thee to give Entertainment to God thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer and Friend. Verily if thou ſhouldeſt once knock at the Gate of my Houſe, I would haſten to open to thee at the firſt Knock, as I opened to <hi>David</hi> my Servant when he groaned at the Rebuke of <hi>Nathan</hi> my Prophet. Therefore, my dearly beloved Son, let my Counſel pleaſe thee; and with ſeaſonable Repentance return un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, thy peaceable King; and I will love thee as a moſt tender-hearted Mother, and will embrace thee, and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh thy Infancy with my moſt pleaſant Milk.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37642:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Concerning the Goodneſs of God, and his Readineſs to forgive.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHither flyeſt thou, dearly beloved Son, who haſt grievouſly offended me? Have I been a barren Wilderneſs unto thee, becauſe thou ſayeſt in thy Heart, I have departed, and I will no more return unto thee. Will a Virgin forget her Attire, or a Bride her Nuptial Ornament? Why then hath thy Soul, which I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpouſed unto my ſelf with the price of my Blood, forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me, and forgotten me days without number? I am Goodneſs it ſelf, which with its Sweetneſs, feedeth all Creatures, than which nothing more lovely can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; and yet through thy great Folly thou ſeekeſt Good out of me. My Son, conſider my Goodneſs, wherewith Rocks are ſoftned, and be thou mollified: Neither believe the falſe Prophets, who foretel falſe Joys beſides me. Verily, if I am the chief Good, of neceſſity whatſoever thou ſeekeſt out of me, is not good for thee, though thou alone ſhouldſt poſſeſs all the Kingdoms of the World, and all things deſirable unto carnal Eyes. It is commonly ſaid, Good is that which all deſign; and yet thou being led aſide by a great Error, art enticed with the pleaſure of things that have the falſe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Goodneſs; but the true eternal and unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Good, thou fooliſhly forſakeſt. O that thou wert wiſe, and hadſt Underſtanding to conſider thy Latter-end! O Son, follow not ſtrange Gods! for ſurely they will turn thy Heart away from true Wiſdom: Thou ſhalt look for Light and not ſee it, neither ſhalt thou behold the Dawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37642:8"/>of the Day. Let my pure Law cleave unto thy inward Parts, and hearken unto the whiſpering Voice of my Secret Teaching, and the Catholick Faith, with which I have inlightned thee. Behold, thou believeſt with a ſincere Faith, that I am Infinite Goodneſs, Beauty, and Wiſdom, with which only the Heart of Man can be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied: Whither then haſtneſt thou, whilſt thou offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt me, but unto Infinite Wickedneſs, Filthineſs, and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, with which thy Soul will be defiled? Is it not greater Wiſdom to adhere unto me, and to be illuminated and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with the Breaſts of my Conſolation, than to be ſo Hunger-ſtarved as not to have a full Meal of the Husks of Swine in the midſt of my Vagabond, and Fugitive Enemies? Return, O prodigal Son, unto thy reſt, and I will embrace thee, when thou returneſt from a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and I will ſay unto my Servant as ſoon as I ſee thee, Bring hither ſpeedily the beſt Robe, put a Ring upon his Hand, and Shooes upon his Feet: For my Bowels will yern upon my dearly beloved Son, whom I have begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and I will rejoyce at thy Converſion as he that findeth much Spoil. For I delight in ſhewing Mercy; and by reaſon of the Greatneſs of my Goodneſs, my Soul melteth at the Groans of Repenting Sinners, and at the Miſery and Sighing of the Poor. Son, remember how tender-hearted I am; whereby thou mayeſt learn how great is the Multitude of my Goodneſs and Sweetneſs. Read my holy Scriptures, and thou wilt wonder at my Readineſs to ſhow Mercy, and to forgive Sinners, and to comfort the Afflicted: Whereby thou wilt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that I am a good Lord, and wilt fear to depart from me, as Death uſeth to be feared. I never lifted up my Spear againſt the Man that was willing to ſerve my moſt gracious Father, though he had ſinned moſt grievouſly. Once <hi>David</hi> groaned; ſaying, I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37642:8"/>and immediately, I put away his Sin. The Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, who had greatly offended me, accuſed himſelf with a few Sighs; and preſently he went down to his Houſe juſtified and joyful in Heart. The wicked Servant owed me Ten thouſand Talents; who falling down craved Mercy of me, and I ſent him away free, and forgave him all the debt. The Woman that was taken in Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery ſtood in fear, and was inſtantly accuſed in my ſight. And I anſwering her very ſweetly, delivered her from Condemnation. I ſhewed a loving Countenance to <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen</hi> the Sinner, and preſently forgave her; ſo that the <hi>Phariſee,</hi> who had invited me, wondred. The Thief that was crucified with me, melted my Heart with one word, and immediately was made Partaker of my Kingdom. Wherefore then is not my Goodneſs, which is eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by ſo many Proofs, acceptable to the Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> but they ſeek ſtrange Conſolations? Shun, O my Son, the Societies of Sinners, and by True Repentance ſeek my Face.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Concerning the Wiſdom of God, from which a Man by Sinning departs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O How fooliſhly haſt thou departed from me, my Son, with <hi>Adam</hi> thy Father, who endeavoured by the forbidden Tree to become like God, knowing Good and Evil! This is not the way of my Wiſdom, which ſavours very ſweetly to the Palate of the Heart. I Wiſdom, who have proceeded from the Mouth of the moſt High, am a moſt beautiful Light, who do illuminate with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Brightneſs the Minds of little ones, who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37642:9"/>commit themſelves to my Diſcipline. But thoſe that are puffed up, and preſumptuous, I caſt away from my Preſence, that they may ſit in Darkneſs, and the Shadow of Death, and may not know how to diſcern between their left Hand and their Right. Wo unto Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whom their own Wickedneſs hath blinded, leſt they ſhould behold me the Sun of Righteouſneſs, and Maſter of Wiſdom; under whoſe Inſtruction they might learn in a moment the Secrets of Heaven, and might become more learned, than if they knew how to number the Stars of Heaven, and the Sand that lies on the Sea-ſhore. Verily, though a Sinner, who departs from me, knew all manner of Learning that is taught in the Univerſities of the World, he would yet know nothing; becauſe he knows not, in whom are all the Treaſures of the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God. And though he ſhould ſpeak with the Tongues of Men and Angels, he would be eſteemed as an Infant in my Heavenly City, becauſe he knows not the Word of God, who makes the Tongues of Infants elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. Seeing then theſe things are ſo, what meaneſt thou, my Son, to bewilder thy ſelf in the various Sciences of Men, in which there is no Salvation, or Satisfaction? Thou being now wearied, return unto me the Fountain of Wiſdom, which is ſweeter than Honey, and I will give thee to drink, and thy Bowels ſhall be enlarged. Thy Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding can reſt in me only, therefore labour not in vain in ſeeking lying Maſters, whom I have not taught. Fly out of the midſt of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſhun the innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Anxieties, with which thy Heart is diſtracted; and I will lead thee into the Wilderneſs, and nouriſh thee, and teach thee my Goodneſs Diſcipline, and Knowledge; ſo that thou ſhalt underſtand more than the Ancients, and excel all the Magicians of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and Soothſayers of the <hi>Chaldeans.</hi> Take away the Filth of thy Mind, dearly
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37642:9"/>beloved Son, and be thou clean, that with pure Eyes thou mayeſt behold my moſt clear Light. And I will give unto thee to know my Myſteries, and to be inflamed with the Love of eternal Wiſdom, which delighteth pure Hearts with unſpeakable Joys: Take a taſte of my Sweetneſs, and thy Eyes ſhall be opened to behold my Myſteries, which are more deſirable than Gold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones, and ſweeter than Honey, and the Honey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb. And thy broken Bones ſhall rejoyce, which I will fill with moſt pure Delights, which I have prepared for Penitents, who return from a ſtrange Land unto the lovely City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where they treaſure up their Riches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Concerning the Peace of God, which is loſt by Sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I A peaceable King, who am magnified above all the Kings of the whole Earth; I do make my Friends Partakers of the Peace, which paſſeth all Underſtanding. For when a Man is in the State of Grace, I dwell in him, as in the Nuptial Bed-chamber, where all things are at Peace; and therein is taſted the moſt ſweet Peace of the Children of God, and therein is heard the moſt ſweet Harmony of the Parts of Man, conſpiring into one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of my Law; which that Man well underſtood, who ſaid: <hi>O God, I will ſing unto thee a new Song, on a Pſaltery of ten Strings will I ſing Praiſe to thee.</hi> This Peace is more precious than Gold, and more deſirable than all the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Riches, and Comforts of the World: Which if the Men of this World ſhould taſte, they would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately deſpiſe all Earthly Loves, and breath after me. Thou
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37642:10"/>therefore, my Son, conſider what thou didſt, when thou departedſt from me. Thou didſt reject my Peace, and it was removed far from thee; and innumerable Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies roſe up againſt thy Soul, who ſleep not, and ſuffer thee not to reſt. Thou thoughteſt that thou ſhouldeſt have and poſſeſs Peace, if thou ſhouldeſt ſatisfie thy Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, and its vain Deſires, living after the manner of the Heathen, who know not me; and yet thou foundeſt no Peace, but Solicitudes, Anxieties, Pangs of Conſcience, Horrors and Fears of my Judgment; as <hi>Cain,</hi> who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving departed from my Preſence, was afraid leſt every one that found him ſhould ſlay him. That hath befaln thee, my Son, which of old befel the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which made not a good uſe of the Habitation of my City <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> For <hi>Judah</hi> was removed becauſe of Affliction and great Bondage, which ſhe fell into by Sinning: She dwelt among the Heathen, and ſound no reſt. O how grievouſly doth the Sinner err, who caſts away from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Peace of the Children of God, and involves him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in infinite doubts! O how unhappily lives the wicked Man, who flyeth, when none purſueth, carrying with himſelf the Damnation of Death, which he hath procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red! How long ſhall I cry and invite thee, unthankful Son, unto the Banquet of my Dainties, where thy inward Parts ſhall enjoy Peace, and rejoyce in the Society of my Peace and Love? Return now, my Son, unto thy Reſt, which I have purchaſed for thee by the Sorrows of Death, and let it pleaſe thee to have one Heart and one Soul with me. Let us now make a Covenant of moſt faithful Agreement, which may have no end. I ſpare thee dearly beloved Friend; neither do I remember the Fault wherewith thou haſt offended me: Give me thy Heart that we may enter into a Covenant of Friendſhip in my Blood, which I have ſhed for thee. Break now the Bonds
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37642:10"/>of thy Neck, O captive Son, and breath after my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; for as for me, I will be thy moſt faithful Helper in times of need, in Tribulation and in Want. I have written thee in the midſt of my Heart, and will never forget thee. Only I require that thou return unto me, and for the future make good uſe of my moſt ſweet Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip; and I will cauſe Righteouſneſs, and abundance of Peace to ariſe in thee, which ſhall endure as long as the Sun and Moon. Behold, my Side opened, and my Hands pierced through with Nails; joyn the Side of thy Heart unto my Side, and thy Hands unto my Hands, and return at length unto the moſt precious Peace of thy Redeemer and Friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Concerning the Protection of God, from which a Man by Sinning departs.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I The Preſerver of Men, take a care of my Servants, as a Nurſe that nouriſheth her little Infant; for he that keepeth <hi>Iſrael</hi> neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps. I keep my dearly beloved Friends as the Apple of my Eye, neither do I ſuffer the Rod of the Wicked to reſt upon the Lot of the Righteous, leſt they being afflicted above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſhould ſtretch forth their Hands to Iniquity. From the beginning of the World it hath not been heard, that any Mother did ſo affectionately love, and keep her only Son, as I, who am more than a Mother to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my righteous ones, and I love their Souls as my moſt pleaſant Brides. They that ſerve me need not be afraid of the Cold of Winter; for all the Servants of my Houſe are cloathed with double Cloathing, for they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37642:11"/>have a good Lord. Wherefore then, my Son, haſt thou departed from me, and expoſed thy ſelf to Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Robbers, who lie in wait for thee, ſaying; God hath forſaken him for his Sins, perſecute and take him, becauſe there is none to deliver him? Who ſhall defend thee from the many Calves, and the ſat Bulls, that have beſet thee round, if thou art not in my keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? All the Beaſts of the Wood will haſten to thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, unleſs they perceive, that I am thy Keeper. Without the Sword ſhall bereave thee, and Terror with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; thou ſhall be a Vagabond, and a Fugitive upon the Earth. Haſt thou not conſidered how Malefactors are afraid, who have offended Earthly Kings? Verily they reſt no where, but are afrighted at every noiſe, as at the Shadow of Death, conſidering leſt the Officers of the King being offended, ſhould ſuddenly fall upon them: Therefore how much more will the fear of Death terrifie thee, if thou be without my Protection, and be delivered as the Servant of Sin unto thy Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors? It is a wonder how mad Sinners are, who have delivered their Souls into the hands of their Enemies, not conſidering that they want my Strength. Return therefore, dearly beloved Son, unto me thy Keeper, and I who have broken the Heads of the Dragons, will defend thee. I will lead thee through a Deſert Land, through the waſte-houling Wilderneſs if thou continueſt in my fear. I will trouble the Princes of <hi>Edom,</hi> and Trembling ſhall take hold on the mighty Men of <hi>Moab,</hi> whilſt thou paſſeſt through the way of Life under my Protection. Return with all thy Heart unto me thy Keeper, and Guide, not ſeeking the weak Helps of the World, and its Followers: And I only will be thy Guide, and I will be unto thee as the Eagle, teaching her young ones to fly, and fluttering over them, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37642:11"/>thou ſhalt know by experience that one day in my Courts and Protection, is better than a thouſand elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: And in the time of diſtreſs I will deliver thee, becauſe thou haſt ſet thy Heart on me, guarding it with a moſt firm Perſwaſion of my Goodneſs and Mercy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Concerning the Loſs of Divine Grace, which the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner falls into.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL the Treaſures of the World compared with my Divine Grace, are Duſt and Aſhes, and are accounted as things of no value. For ſo great is the Height, the Dignity, and the Beauty of my Grace, that it ſtirs up great Admiration in the Minds of them, that rightly conceive thereof. Whereby it comes to paſs, that my Servants having their Eyes enlightned, are moved with inward Grief and Compaſſion for their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, when they fall into any dangerous Sin. Which if thou, my Son, ſhouldeſt well conſider of, thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuddenly return unto me, being moved with the Greatneſs of the Calamity, which thou haſt faln into by Sinning. Thy Soul was my moſt pleaſant Bride, in Cloathing of Gold, and in Raiment of divers Colours, whoſe Beauty the Sun and Moon did admire. So great was its Grace, whilſt it remained faithful to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of its Eſpouſals, that it wonderfully delighted my Eyes. The Daughter of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was adorned with Jewels beautiful as a Dove, ſhining very brightly, and endued with a very lovely Comelineſs. She was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to her Pattern, in compariſon of whom the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Stars do not ſhine. She was greatly enriched with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37642:12"/>the true Riches of my Vertues, which neither Ruſt nor Moth can corrupt. But from the Daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> all her Beauty was departed, when ſhe had ſinned, and ſhe fell from ſo great Felicity into ſo extream Calamity, that the Heavens were aſtoniſhed at this Change. For, my Son, ſo great is the Filthineſs and Shameſulneſs of Sin, which thou haſt committed, that thou art become a Leper; ſearful to look upon becauſe of thy intolerable Rottenneſs, and Meat for Worms that are crawling out upon thee. What is this? How is the Pleaſantneſs of my Paradice vaniſhed, and the fruitful Land turned into Barrenneſs, for the Wickedneſs of them that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? How hath thy Soul departed from me, contrary to the Covenant of thine Eſpouſals, and hath been defiled with many Lovers, who have corrupted her. Return therefore, my Son, unto my Grace and Friendſhip, and unto the Light of my Countenance; neither be ſo foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh as to deſire to live any longer in ſo great Miſery and Want. Put on the precious and white Wedding-Garment, that thou mayeſt be acceptable to me, and ſit down at the Great Supper, with my dearly beloved Elect. I counſel thee to buy of me, without Silver, the Royal Apparel, that thou mayeſt walk through the Street of the Holy City, cloathed in Purple amongſt the famous Sons of <hi>Sion,</hi> who are cloathed with the fine Gold of my Love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:37642:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Concerning the Communion of Saints, which a Man loſeth by Sinning.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WO to him that is alone, for if he fall, he hath none to help him up. But bleſſed is the Man who enjoys the Communion of all that fear and love Me, and keep my moſt pleaſant Commandments. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily he that is united unto me by Grace, continues alſo united unto all my Members, who live the Heavenly Life of my Grace, than which nothing more lovely is found in the Land of the Living. My Angels and Holy Men, joyned to me by Grace, are moſt faithful Friends of all Men that love me. And then, my Son, when thou didſt the things that pleaſe me, thou hadſt theſe Conſolations and Priviledges of the Righteous, which are more precious than all Gold. Thou waſt joyned to my Saints, whoſe Names are written in the Book of Life; and all their Goods belonged unto thee, being my living Member. And I the Head of the Church, my Spouſe, did influence thee with lively Motions of my Love, wherewith I move the Hearts of them that love me, and ſeek my Face. For my Spirit preſſed thee forward, and ſtirred thee up, and inſlamed thee with ardent Deſire of the eternal Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewith my wearied Souldiers coming from the Earth, are ſatisfied. But now thy Viſage through Sin, is become black as a Coal, and thou lyeſt down in Deſtruction, which thou haſt procured to thy ſelf, being deprived of the Society of the Saints, which is the utmoſt Calamity. What friends wilt thou find,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37642:13"/>my Son, if my Friends favour thee not? What Society will profit thee, whilſt thou wanteſt the Society of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Saints? Who will comfort thee in Diſtreſs, if thou dwelleſt with Scorpions, and art not at Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Heaven? Return, my Son, return unto the Fellowſhip of the Citizens of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> my City, and to the Feaſts that are celebrated with the Communion of moſt pleaſant Love; that thou mayeſt live happily the remainder of thy mortal Life, and afterwards may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt paſs unto the Communion of the Church trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, where there will be moſt ſweet Peace, and a full and perfect Union. Depart from the Tabernacles of the Wicked, who love not thee, nor themſelves; for he that loves Iniquity, hates his own Soul. It will be much more profitable and delightful to thee, my Son, to aſſociate thy ſelf with my living Members, and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Veſſels, that thou mayeſt learn Wiſdom in the School of my Meekneſs, and mayeſt grow up with the Nouriſhment of Men come to years, that grow up to the meaſure of Love, which is higher than Heaven. The World paſſeth away, and the Luſt thereof; but the Union of my Love will never paſs away, but will joyn with Me, my moſt beloved Servants, for whom I have appointed a Kingdom that they may eat and drink at my Table in the Banquet of the Dainties of my Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:37642:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Concerning Inconſtancy, which a Sinner falls into.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>JEruſalem</hi> hath ſinned a great Sin; therefore ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came unſtable, and could find no Reſt: A Fool changes as the Moon. Wherefore ſeeing every Sinner is a Fool, he ſuffers the Puniſhment of his own Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion; never continuing in the ſame ſtate, but chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Purpoſe every hour. He hath departed from his Firmneſs and Conſtancy, which he had in Me, his God and Keeper, who change not. And therefore he wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in Uncertainty, not knowing whither to go, and finding no Reſt for the ſole of his Foot. All his Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors over-take him between the ſtraits; and he deſiring to eſcape free, changes places perpetually, until his own Evils take him in Deſtruction, while he is flying away. Wo to the Soul, that hath departed from Me! He will ſind Torments every where, and day and night Sleep will depart from his Eyes. To day the Sinner ſeeks Friends, to morrow he ſhuns them, becauſe they are unfaithful. To day he is bent upon Games, to morrow he laments; becauſe by living riotouſly he hath conſumed his Subſtance. To day he ſeeks the Honours of the World, to morrow he ſhuns them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing marked with Infamy for his Sins. What then art thou minding, my Son, who ſitteſt upon the Wheel of the World, which is always turning? How is it, that thou doſt not return unto Me, who am thy Safety, Vertue, and Conſtancy? Haſt thou not learned by dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Experience, that the Thoughts of Mortal Men are fearful, and their Fore-caſts uncertain, which proceed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37642:14"/>without Order unto the end? Know aſſuredly, my Son, that without my Mercy thou art the dry Stuble, and a Leaf driven with the Eaſt-wind, which can no where find Reſt. Sometimes thou wilt be joyful, and anon ſorrowful; to morrow thou wilt lament for thy Infirmity, and the next day thou wilt be terrified with the fear of Death. Sometimes the care of Temporal things, ſometimes Ambition, ſometimes Thirſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Hunger will torment thee; unleſs thou repent, and caſt thy care on Me, and offer thy ſelf wholly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Me on the Altar of thy Heart. If thou ſhalt ſeek Me with all thy Heart, nothing ſhall trouble thee; neither Death nor Life, nor the World, nor Hell, nor any other Creature viſible or inviſible. For by the Teſtimony of thy Conſcience thou ſhalt be as the Lyon, that is ſtrongeſt among Beaſts, and turneth not away for any. I will confirm thee who waſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Inconſtancy of <hi>Adam</hi> thy Father, and I will ſtrengthen thee with my moſt mighty Hand. I will make thee a Pillar of Iron, and a Wall of Braſs, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Enemies of thy Soul. They ſhall fight againſt thee, but they ſhall not prevail againſt thee, becauſe I will change thee, being a Penitent, into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man, and make thee Partaker of my Grace and Valour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37642:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Concerning the Remorſe of Conſcience, wherewith a Sinner is tormented.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MY Son, unleſs thou return to Me with all thy Heart, thy Wickedneſs will correct thee, and thy Backſliding will reprove thee; for by what things any Man ſins, by the ſame he ſhall be puniſhed. It is a juſt Judgment, that the Sinner who hath forſaken Me his God, ſhould feel within himſelf Remorſe of Conſcience and Anguiſh, ariſing from the fear of Death and Hell. It is a juſt Judgment, that amongſt the forbidden Joys of the World, wherewith he ſeeks to be delighted contrary to my Law, he ſhould be pierced with the ſting of a Heart groaning and foreſeeing its own Damnation. The Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Death fight againſt a Sinner, though he ſeeks for Joys; neither can a wicked Man have Peace, who is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by his own Conſcience, from which he cannot fly. This Remorſe riſeth out of Sin, as a Worm out of Timber, and ſhews that I am a juſt Judge, and that the Sinner is a Betrayer, who ſold me for a ſmall price. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on theſe things, my Son, and ſee that it is an evil and bitter thing that thou haſt forſaken Me thy Lord and Beneſactor, and that my Fear was not before thee: Doſt thou not ſee that all things fall out unhappily to thee, whilſt thou flyeſt from me? and that with Anxiety of Mind thou drinkeſt the troubled Waters of the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> whereas by my Grace thou mayeſt return into the dearly beloved City of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and drink of the pure Water of <hi>Jordan,</hi> where thou mayeſt waſh, and be made whiter than Snow. Wherefore then reſiſteſt thou the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:37642:15"/>Impulſes of my Love, calling and inviting thee to my Friendſhip? Caſt away from thee, my Son, the five Yokes of Oxen, which thou haſt fooliſhly bought, and take willingly upon thee my one and moſt ſweet Yoke, where thou ſhalt not be wearied with the Prickings of Conſcience, but ſhalt find reſt to thy wearied Soul. Seek the Heavenly Tranquillity, and the Peace which paſſeth all Underſtanding, and reſt from that Anxiety where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou art vexed. Call unto me, and I will anſwer thee with my Divine Inſpirations, which will beget true Joys, and compoſe thy troubled Spirit. I will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort thee, and ſpeak inwardly to thy Heart, if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto me, and praiſe me with Uprightneſs of Heart, when thou haſt obtained Liberty and Reſt, and other moſt precious Priviledges of the Children of God. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe now the Counſels of the Men of the World, who torment thy Heart, and follow my one and moſt health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Counſel; and thou ſhalt ſee how I ſcatter all the Plots of thy Enemies; and create in thee a new Spirit, whereby thy Age may be renewed as the Eagles, that thou mayeſt enjoy my moſt lovely Peace and Security.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Concerning the Hardneſs of Heart, which a Sinner falls into.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Am righteous, and I love Righteouſneſs, and my Countenance beholds the Upright. The Sinner hath rejected me, and reſiſted my innumerable Inſpirations, whereby I endeavoured to mollifie his Heart. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I reject him, and withhold my Rain that it drops not upon him. I invited <hi>Pharaoh</hi> by outward Signs,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37642:15"/>which I wrought by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> my Servant, and by inward Inſpirations, which he unhappy Sinner felt: But when he reſiſted my great Mercy, I ſuffered his Heart to be hardened, more than the Flintſtone, and the hardeſt Rocks, until he perſecuted <hi>Iſrael</hi> my People, and was drowned, as Lead in the mighty Waters. I anointed <hi>Saul</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he was little in his own Eyes, and followed me like a Boy of one Year old: But, after he began and continued to reſiſt my many Motions and Inſpirations, I threw him away, ſo that he fell upon his own Sword, and died fearfully. I handled unhappy <hi>Judas</hi> my Diſciple, as a loving and faithful Man; but after that he reſiſted my ſweet Words and Inſpirations, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Heart againſt me, I ſent him away; ſo that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming like a Devil, hanged himſelf, and burſt aſunder in the midſt, and all his Bowels guſhed out. What then doſt thou expect, my Son, who haſt ſinned, and depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Me? Wherefore doſt thou continue in the State of Damnation, hardning thy Heart, leſt it ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome with my infinite Sweetneſs and Patience? Shall I for ever knock at the Gate of thy Houſe, that thy Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may be tamed? Return, O Son, unto thy right Wits; neither caſt thy ſelf into extream Danger, ſo as to make thy Wound uncureable. Haſt thou not heard that it will be ill with a hard Heart at laſt; and that a Sinner is held with the Cords of his Sins? Beware, my Son, of this great Evil, and conſider what I require of thee. When a Sinner cometh into the depth of Sins, he deſpiſeth it; but before he deſpiſes it, he is touched and moved with the inward Inſpirations of my Goodneſs; but afterwards by degrees he waxes cold, and hath leſs ſenſe of my Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſes, until his ſtony Heart becoming unſenſible, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not my Admonitions; but as an untamed Horſe, he runs through the Meadows of the World, haſtening
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:37642:16"/>to eternal Fire. Wo to thee, unleſs thou return ſpeedily to Me! Remember thy Salvation and my Glory, which I have prepared for thoſe, who repenting in ſincerity waſh their Garments in my Blood. Uſe now the Remedies of Mercy, leſt thou be hardned, and delivered up to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe. If thou ſhalt hearken to me, I wilt melt the Ice of thy Heart, and my Wind ſhall blow, and the Waters of Compunction ſhall flow; with which thy Fllth ſhall be waſhed away. Embrace this wholeſom Counſel of thy Redeemer, who is ready to ſpare thee, and to amend thy Condition: If thou return to me, I will imprint a ſenſe of Contrition and Love in thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Parts, and thou ſhalt rejoyce in the Renovation of thy Heart, as Conquerors rejoyce in taking of the Prey, and thou ſhalt celebrate thy Regeneration; and being made whole, thou ſhalt ſing of my invincible Mercies, that are ſweeter than the Honey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Concerning Deſperation, which a Sinner ſometimes falls into.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Conſider, my Son, that there is no other name under Heaven, by which thou muſt be ſaved, but mine. Be not deceived in putting thy Truſt in the King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who is a broken Reed; upon which, if any Man leans, it will pierce through his Hand. I have overcome the World, Death, and Hell; and therefore he that offends Me, and ſeeks Refuge in the Favour and Delights of Men, who are not Partakers of my Victory, falls into Dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mind, which is a very bitter Puniſhment. He wants my Grace, which begets the hope of eternal good things;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37642:16"/>and ſeeing that he does nothing ſutable to the hope of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life, he is broken and weakened, ſo that he falls into a moſt grievous Deſperation, which reſembles the State of the Damned: This is the fruit of Ambition, which ſeeks the Honours of Men, that are written in the Earth. This is the fruit of Covetouſneſs, which with an unſatiable deſire lays up Treaſure in the Earth. This is the fruit of Luxury, which is drunk with the Pleaſures of the Fleſh, and cares not for the moſt pure Joys of my Spirit. This is the fruit of Anger, which makes the feet of Men ſwift to ſhed Blood; and cares not for being reckoned amongſt my meek Servants, who ſhall poſſeſs the Land of the Living. Moreover, this is the fruit of all Sins, when Wickedneſs increaſeth, and the Soul ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors Good, by which Men come to eternal Life. What doſt thou then, my Son? Why lyeſt thou in the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble State of Enmity to Me, which brings forth the fruit of Deſperation, haſtening Death and Damnation? How is it that thou doſt not pity thy own Soul, which languiſhes for want of Strength? Conſider thy Diſſoluteneſs and Madneſs, which makes thee run into Hell-fire, and to take no care of eternal Salvation, as if thou hadſt no hope. Thou doſt fooliſhly, my Son, in deſpairing, and not conſidering that I am omnipotent, and can in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deliver thee from the horrible Pit, and the miry Clay: Caſt away from thee the Filth and Weights of Sin, which bow thy Back, and drive thee to Deſpair; and breath after Me, the Author of thy Hope and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, and thou ſhalt be delivered from the grievous Bondage wherewith thou art oppreſſed, and thou ſhalt be ſweetly refreſhed with the Breathings of my Spirit. Return to me by timely Repentance, which begets a Godly Sorrow, and alſo rejoyceth the Soul that is renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Me, and receives from Me the Pledge of the eternal
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:37642:17"/>Inheritance. So thou ſhalt hope, and thy troubled Soul ſailing through the great Sea, ſhall be kept ſafe by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Anchor of a moſt firm hope, which I have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for thee by my moſt precious Blood, and uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable Love.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>Concerning <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief, which a Sinner is in danger to fall into.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I The Son of the moſt high God, am the Light of the World; and with juſt Judgment puniſh a Sinner who hates me, with inward Darkneſs, wherewith the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is darkned: Which Evil is ſo grievous and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable, that ſometimes an unhappy Sinner by multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying his Faults departs ſo far from true Light, that he falls into Unbelief. He hath departed from Me, and loved Earthly good things more than Me: Whereby it come to paſs that his Will being depraved, ſo corrupts the true Judgment of the Underſtanding, that at length he loſes the Catholick Faith. So thou mayeſt ſee, my Son, what hath happened unto many Sinners; who when they had firſt believed in me, by aggravating the Sins of Covetouſneſs, Pride, Gluttony, or Luxury, have erred from the Faith, and pierced themſelves through with many Sorrows. Wo to thoſe that hate my moſt pure Light, whereby the eternal and unchangeable Good is known, and preferred before created good things. It had been better for thoſe Men, if they had not been born. For it is extream Unhappineſs to err from my Faith, and to caſt away my Yoke with a darkned Underſtanding. And thou therefore, my Son, conſidering what hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37642:17"/>unto others like thy ſelf, return unto me; leſt perhaps being weary of my immaculate Law, thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to have hard Thoughts of my Goodneſs; and giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing looſe reins to thy Heart through the Love of Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things, thou give thy ſelf up to wicked Doings, and ungodly Luſts, unto the prodigious denying of my Faith. My Son, look whither thou art going, whilſt thou ceaſeſt not to ſin; be not cruel to thy ſelf in running ſwiftly to Deſtruction; take heed leſt thou deſpiſe my Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with which I inſtruct thee; ſtop not thy Ears, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeduced with carnal Love, which drowns multitudes of Men into Perdition. The time is ſhort, traffick till I come to reward thee with eternal Life, or with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Fire. If thou ſhalt take away, from the midſt of thee, thy Sins and thy Idols, and return and call upon Me thy God and Redeemer, and Preſerver, I will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten thine Eyes, leſt at any time thou ſleep the Sleep of Death; I will preſerve thee, and my Candle ſhall ſhine upon thine Head: And thou ſhalt rejoyce in my moſt pleaſant and moſt bleſſed Light, wherewith I will direct thy Paths, in the night of the mortal Life, leading thee to my bright-ſhining Glory, in the ways that lead to eternal Life. I will open thy Eyes with the Beam of my infinite Light; and thou being awaked as it were out of a heavy Sleep, ſhalt wonder how in the by-paſt time, thou didſt walk in Darkneſs, and in the Shadow of Death. And thou ſhalt love Me thy Deliverer with all thy Heart, and ſhalt honour Me with the Sacrifice of perpetual Praiſe. Ariſe ſpeedily, my dearly beloved Son, ariſe from the Darkneſs and Horror of Hell, where thou lyeſt, and receive the Light of Heaven, which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce thee, before the laſt night come; which will be the laſt Puniſhment of Sinners, who deſpiſe my preſent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:37642:18"/>Inſpirations and Mercies. Meditate on theſe things in the inner Chamber of thy Heart, and caſt thy Eyes upon Me the Sun of Righteouſneſs, who am deſirous to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten thee, and to fill thy dearly beloved Soul with the bright-ſhining Glory of the Saints of Light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Concerning the unhappy Death of a Sinner.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Sinner, whilſt he lives, runs through the Fields of the World like an Ox, ſatted for the Slaughter. The miſerable Man conſiders not that he will be taken by Death, as a Highway-Man lying in wait. That being bound in the Chains of Hell, he may pay unto the utmoſt Farthing. He drinks, he eats, he plays, he laughs, he ſwears and blaſphems, and in the very time whilſt he is ſinning without reſtraint, Sickneſs and Death comes ſuddenly upon him, and he is called to Judgment. O how bitter a Grief is it to be called to Death! O how great Trembling and Horror takes hold on the Sinner, when he ſees that by a moſt grievous Death, he is ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from all things which he dearly loved! O how lamentably, ſaith he, in that diſtreſs, the Sorrows of Death have compaſſed me, and the Pains of Hell have taken hold upon me! Wo to the wicked Man, when he dies, upon whom all the Billows of Sorrow and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ſuddenly ruſh, that he may have a fore-taſte of the Torments of Hell, who did not breath after eternal Conſolations. Now the riotous Banquets are paſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; now the ungodly Games are gone: Now Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Friends have failed: Now Riches profit not;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37642:18"/>and whatſoever was delightful, is turned into Matter of Deſolation and Deſpair. The unhappy Soul, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed my Inſpirations, is afraid to go out of the Body into everlaſting Flames; and flys back as far as it can, if ſo be it may find any that can comfort it in that diſtreſs. But it reſiſts in vain, becauſe the hour of Death is at hand, and the time of its giving up all its deſireable things, which it had in the days of old, when it tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my moſt ſweet Law. All its Sins, as a terrible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, are ſet before it, that it may ſee how ſad and bitter an end follows the by-paſt Joys. The Devils like rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Dogs, ſtand in expectation of their Prey which is tyed with innumerable Chains of its own Sins, that it may be dragged to Puniſhment. The fooliſh Man when he had time, took no care to be reconciled unto Me; and in the laſt hour he hath not any whom he may look to for help. All his Perſecutors over-take him between the ſtraits, and deſire cruelly to ſuck up his Blood; and then the Sentence of my Juſtice being pronounced, the Veſſel of Wrath, fitted for Deſtruction, is halled to Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. This is the Lot of an unrighteous Man, whom Evils do overtake in Deſtruction. What thinkeſt thou then, my Son, who haſt ſinned? What doſt thou ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect? Is not thy Mind terrified at the hearing of theſe things, which a Sinner dying ſuffers againſt his Will? Turn then to thy God, who can deliver thee from the Wrath to come, and comfort thee when thou art going out of this Life, by his infinite Grace, and his uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveable Mercy. Be greatly afraid of my Wrath and Juſtice, whilſt thou art alive, that at thy Death thou mayeſt find my Fatherly Compaſſion: For they that in their life time fear me as a ſevere Judge, in their Death they find Me as a moſt bountiful Father. Bleſſed are they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37642:19"/>who obſerve my Ways with all their Heart, being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of their latter end: They ſhall not be afraid of the Terror of the Night, when they ſhall ſpeak with their Enemies in the Gate; to wit, when they ſhall paſs out of this Life: After which will follow the eternal Night of Sinners, or the eternal Light of the Righteous, whom I have loved. Follow me, my Son, and let my Law cleave to thy inward Parts, and the Torment of Death ſhall not ſeize upon thee, but thou ſhalt reſt in a joyful and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Peace.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
